<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Holy time of Christmas defended against non-conformists and all others its prophaners and opposers, or, A discourse shewing that a religious observation of Christmas is apostolical and worthy every good Christian</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10409811</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10409811</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1386:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Holy time of Christmas defended against non-conformists and all others its prophaners and opposers, or, A discourse shewing that a religious observation of Christmas is apostolical and worthy every good Christian</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 [i.e. 10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Christmas --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44969:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44969:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HOLY TIME OF CHRISTMAS Defended, Againſt <hi>NON-CONFORMISTS,</hi> and all others its Prophaners and Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>OR, A Diſcourſe, ſhewing, That a Religious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of CHRISTMAS is Apoſtolical, and Worthy every good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44969:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44969:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Christmas</hi> Defended againſt it's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners.</head>
            <p>UNhappy times in which we live! That we ſhould all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that ſixteen Hundred years ago, a certain Man, who was alſo God, called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> was born in a Stable for the Salvation of Mankind; and yet, that there ſhould be certain amongſt us, who ſhould count it a piece of Religion, not to keep Holy the Day, on the which our ſaid Great Redeemer was born: O unhappy Times! O croſs Manners of miſ-inſtructed <hi>Zelots!</hi> Does not Reaſon, the Light of God within us, tell us, that if the Conſubſtantial Son of the Almighty, has been ſo Good, as for our ſakes to become Man, cloathing himſelf with the Raggs of our Mortality: We ought with Joy and Thankſgiving to remember ſo high a Favour? And does not the ſame Reaſon and Experience teach us, that the ſetting a part that particular Day, as near as we can gueſs, on which ſome notable Accident has happened, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it, does ſtrangely help us, more livelily, freſhly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionatly to commemorate the ſaid Wonder? Tell me candidly your Thoughts. Should we by no other Memorial but the Hiſtory of <hi>Boſcobel,</hi> relate to Poſterity, the wonderful Reſtauration of our Gracious Soveraign, how little knowledge, and how faint a Belief think you would there be all over <hi>England,</hi> of that ſtrange Wonder and all it's circumſtances a thouſand years hence? We cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably imagin, but the generality of the common People would be wholly ignorant of it; and we may without raſh Judgment ſurmize, there would not want Cavilling Wits, who would call in queſtion the whole Story, and for ſome ſeemingly, unlikely circumſtances, condemn the whole Narration as fabulous, or at beſt, of very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and uncertain credit: So that in effect, Poſterity ſome Ages hence, would have little more Belief of that undoubted Hiſtory, than we have now of the Fable of <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwick,</hi> But let us go on as we have begun, to commemorate that ſtrange accident, with a Day ſet a part on purpoſe, Religiouſly to be obſerved in all the Pariſhes of <hi>England,</hi> by publick Prayers, and Sermons, ſuited to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44969:3"/>occaſion, and 'tis not poſſible, but till Dooms-day come, there ſhall be an aſſured Belief, and freſh Memory of it in the generality of all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hearts. Has Nature then made us ſo cunning for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to keep in memory what we have a mind ſhould never be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? And can you think Grace, or the Holy Ghoſt was wanting to make the firſt Planters of Chriſtianity ſo wiſe, as to think upon a happy Expedient; how all Generations all the World over, might have a freſh Memory, and aſſured Faith of the wonderful Nativity of their Lord and Saviour; eſpecially when the lively Memory of the ſaid their Lord's Nativity, with all it's circumſtances is ſtrangely conducing to the Salvation of the World? But why do I urge the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Reaſon and Nature? Did not infinit unerring Wiſdom, and the God of Nature uſe this very Means, to propagate to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the Memory of the ſtupendious Wonders, he wrought amidſt his beloved People the <hi>Jews,</hi> by the hand of his Servant <hi>Moſes?</hi> Read from the ſixth Chapter to the fourteenth, in the Book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and take notice of thoſe ſtrange VVonders Almighty God wrought, to compel <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> to let his choſen People go into the VVilderneſs to worſhip him; turning all the Rivers of <hi>Egypt</hi> into Blood, filling the whole Country, in their very houſes with Froggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and finally, killing all their Firſt-born both of Man and Beaſts. And now becauſe a lively Memory of theſe VVonders to all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, would be of admirable benefit to every Age; as well to preſerve in them a ſtrong actual Faith of the true God, the Author of all thoſe Miracles, as a Holy Dread of the ſame Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and care to obſerve his Commandements: Almighty God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that for ever, that very day, on which his People came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſhould be Solemn and Sacred, and obſerved with ſuch Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as might make Poſterity even ſee their Anceſtors going out of <hi>Egypt</hi> many hundreds of years before. They muſt kill a Lamb, and eat the fleſh of the ſame Lamb with Unleavened Bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in token of what their Anceſtors did in like manner in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the great haſte in which they departed, with unleavened Dough on their backs: and for ever offer to Almighty God their Firſt-born, both of Man and Beaſts, in memory of his killing the Firſtlings of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and ſparing theirs. And this account they were to give of this Ceremonial obſervance; when they ſhould in future Generations be asked the reaſon of it by their Children. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. v. 14. <hi>When thy Son ſhall ask thee to Morrow, ſaying, What is this? Thou ſhalt anſwer him; in a ſtrong hand the Lord brought us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44969:3"/>out of the Land of</hi> Egypt: <hi>For when</hi> Pharaoh <hi>was hardned, and would not let us goe, the Lord killed all the Firſt-born in the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>from the Firſt born of Man to the Firſtling of Beaſts; therefore I ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord all that opens the Womb of the Maſculine Sex, and all the Firſt-begotten of my Sons I redeem.</hi> Such a proviſion as this, made it utterly impoſſible to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ever to forget for all Generations, what the Almighty had wrought in favour of their Anceſtors in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And he muſt be out of his VVits, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of common ſenſe, that could queſtion a matter of Fact, ſo ſolemnly immemorially commemorated, and ſo particularly recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Book; which a whole People time out of mind has venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a moſt true Hiſtory. For had the Rivers of <hi>Egypt</hi> not been turned into Blood, (the like I ſay of the reſt of the VVonders) no man could have had the impudence to have committed to VVriting as moſt certain Truths, what thouſands muſt neceſſarily have known to be moſt notorious Lyes. Much leſs could any one have prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with many thouſands, in a moſt ſerious and ſolemn manner to commemorate yearly with thankſgiving to God, what they all knew had never happened.</p>
            <p>And can it now enter into any Chriſtian mans heart to think, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was more faithful and careful to preſerve in the Memories of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the VVonders the Almighty wrought to deliver that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular People from under the Bondage of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> Then was <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, to keep in the freſh memory of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the ſtupendious VVonders wrought to deliver the whole VVorld, from the Eternal ſlavery of Sin and Devils? Let it be. Four of our Lords followers, have left written Memorials of his Birth, Life, Death, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion into Heaven. But had all his firſt Miſſionaries to the VVorld, ordained in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty converted by them to the Chriſtian Faith, that they ſhould yearly ſpend the Day of his Nativity (which they might eaſily learn from his Holy Mother) in Prayer, Reading, Hearing, and Meditating that Myſtery with all it's circumſtances, and the ends for which it was ſo wrought: VVould not ſuch an Obſervation as this in every Chriſtian Pariſh in the VVorld, have ſtrangely conduced to a pious, profitable, grateful memory of that Miracle of Love, of God's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a little Infant for the Salvation of the VVorld? And this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks ſhould be ſufficient to ſatisfie any reaſonable man, that the keeping Holy, by a yearly Obſervation, of the ſacred time of our deer Lord's Nativity, was not only worthy the Holy Apoſtles Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44969:4"/>but alſo that it cannot be well underſtood, how they could be faithful in their Office, without the making of ſuch an Ordination, or at leaſt without leaving Power and Charge to their Succeſſors ſo to ordain. Such Ordinations being abſolutely neceſſary to poſterity at a long diſtance; howſoever, leſs needful they might be, to them who lived ſo near the time, when that and the other Myſteries of our Lord Jeſus were acted. Nor let us deceive our ſelves and poſterity, by pretending to remember our Lord's Nativity every Day; too ſad Experience telling us, this is the way ſeldom or never, ſoundly and heartily to think of it. In our own Country, what's become of all memory of <hi>Gowry's</hi> Conſpiracy, for want of a day to remember it? And had not the fifth of <hi>November</hi> been ſet a part particularly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi> but had every one been left to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it every day in all likelyhood the memory of that horrid Plot had been by this time quite loſt in the memories of the vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>But all that I have hitherto been ſaying, only ſhews, that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of a particular time to remember our Lord's Nativity, was worthy of the Holy Apoſtles; but what evidence have we that the Holy Apoſtles have actually made any ſuch Ordination? Why, what evidence would you have? Indeed they have written no Book to recommend the Obſervation of any particular day to Poſterity; but if they have taught ſuch an Obſervation by word of mouth, to all the Countries in the World, where they preached the Goſpel; is not this ſufficient? Let us then in our thoughts, Travel into the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chriſtian Countries of the World, and ſee what they obſerve. And firſt let us take a view of our own Native Country, and enquire when we began, upon the 25th. of <hi>December,</hi> every year particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, to lay aſide all our worldly Affairs, and with Prayers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Holy Exerciſes, to remember our deer Lord's Birth? The old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man alive, can tell us no beginning of this our practice. No Chronicles, no Annals give us any account of it's beginning neither. They tell us indeed, that St. <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> not long after our Bleſſed Saviour's Departure into Heaven, brought Chriſtianity into our Country; but they do not tell us of any one ſince that time, who enjoyned us to keep <hi>Chriſtmas-Day</hi> Holy. The ſame Annals tell us, that about the year ſix hundred, one <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with certain Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons came from <hi>Rome</hi> to convert our Nation, the over-run by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel <hi>Saxons,</hi> from Paganiſm to Chriſtianity. They tell us alſo, that the ſame <hi>Auſtin,</hi> found certain <hi>Britiſh</hi> Chriſtians driven into <hi>Wales</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44969:4"/>by the <hi>Saxons;</hi> and make mention alſo how the ſaid <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the Chriſtian <hi>Brittains,</hi> differed about certain Ceremonies in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and moreover, upon what Sunday they ſhould keep <hi>Eaſter</hi> Day; both agreeing <hi>Eaſter</hi> Day was to be kept; the one holding upon the 14th. of the Moon of <hi>March,</hi> in caſe it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the Sunday, the other not till the Sunday following. But now had they differed about the keeping of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day, and that ſo, as one ſhould have ſaid, a day was to be kept, and preciſely the 25th. of <hi>December,</hi> and the other ſhould have contended no Day at all was to be kept: This would have been a more notorious Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, than upon what Sunday <hi>Eaſter</hi> was to be ſolemnized; and conſequently would have been taken notice of by our Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers. Hence I infer, the <hi>Britains</hi> kept holy <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day, before the coming of <hi>Auſtin.</hi> For it cannot be doubted, but <hi>Auſtin</hi> brought from <hi>Rome</hi> the Religion that was then practiſed at <hi>Rome.</hi> And 'tis manifeſt that at <hi>Rome,</hi> they then, and many years before kept Holy the day of our Lord's Nativity. For we have Sermons preached at <hi>Rome</hi> upon the day of our Lord's Nativity, by St. <hi>Leo</hi> Pope, above a hundred years before. Nor let any one be afraid of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her way of VVorſhip thus early; the Church of <hi>England</hi> willingly appeals to the Faith and Practice of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Cities, for the firſt ſix hundred years after our Bleſſed Saviour. Beſides, had the Obſervation of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> in our Nation, been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun ſince our Converſion to Chriſtianity by <hi>Auſtin,</hi> our Chronicles would make mention, what National Synod or Council, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be ſo univerſally obſerved, as it has been time out of mind in every Pariſh in <hi>England.</hi> Should any Forreiner that comes into our Country, take notice of the ſtanding of our Plows, the shutting up of our Shops, and the frequenting of <hi>Divine Service</hi> in every Parish, upon the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> he would inſtantly conclude, we never fell upon ſuch a Practice by chance; but that it was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and ordained by ſome Soveraign power <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> The like Diſcourſe will every rational man make, upon the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Religious Obſervations of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day: To wit, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fell upon ſuch an Obſervance by chance; but either we were all taught ſo by the firſt Planters of Chriſtanity in our Nation; or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned ſo to do by ſome Supreme Authority ſince; but our Annals making no mention of any ſuch Ordination, 'tis rightly concluded, we were ſo taught by our firſt Chriſtian Maſters.</p>
            <p>But if you give a little more ſcope to your Thoughts, and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44969:5"/>that not only <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>Holland, Germany, France, Spain, Italy,</hi> and other Chriſtian Country's, have Immemorially from their firſt Converſion to Chriſtianity, kept Holy the Day of our Lords Nativity: Nor is there any mention of any General Council, or other Univerſal Authority's impoſing any ſuch Obſervation upon them: this Reflection will compel you to acknowledg this Practice muſt needs have been taught, the ſeveral Nations of Chriſtendom, by the firſt Preachers of the Goſpel the Holy Apoſtles. And remarkable to my preſent purpoſe, is the Rule of the Great St. <hi>Auguſtin:</hi> VVhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we find, univerſally practiſed over all the Chriſtian VVorld, we ſafely Conclude, either to have been Ordained by the Apoſtles or ſome General Council, for that it cannot be preſumed, that whole Nations could by chance fall upon the Religious Obſervation of the ſame Day, or other Ceremonial Right. And he whom ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as this does not ſatisfy; but he ſtill Doubts &amp; Diſputes; How can he be ſure the Apoſtles ever taught any ſuch Obſervation? Such an one I ſay let him take heed; for he is dangerouſly diſpoſed to throw away the whole New Teſtament. For how can he tell St. <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote this Book, St. <hi>Luke</hi> that, and ſo of the reſt, but by the univerſal immemorial Teſtimony of ſeveral Chriſtian Countrys. If Almighty God will Oblige me to keep ſuch Daies Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as were ſo appointed, and reverence ſuch Books as Divine, as were by Divine Inſpiration written, ſixteen Hundred Years before I was born, he cannot reaſonably expect I ſhould know and diſtinguiſh either the one or the other, but by the immemorial Teſtimonys of my Anceſtors in ſeveral Countries. But how at the Day of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I ſhould Anſwer the refuſal of ſuch a Book, or the Non-Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of ſuch a Day; So immemorially recommended by my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, I cannot tell. It belongs to the providence of our Bleſſed Saviour to take care, that no Age ſhould be ſo deviliſhly malitious, univerſally to tell their Children, a Book of their own forging (the like may be ſaid of a Holy-Day or other Ritual Obſervance) was written by a Holy Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, ſome hundred of Years before. One Man may be preſumed to be ſo Malicious, whole Nations never did, nor ever can do any ſuch thing. Nor does the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this differ from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as if ſhe thought what the Apoſtles VVrit, was of greater Authority then what they Taught, or Ordained. She willingly admits all Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of which ſhe can have good proof, that they come from the Apoſtles. Such are the Obſervations of <hi>Chriſtmaſs, Lent, Eaſter, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44969:5"/>
            <p>But if <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day was taught the VVorld by the Apoſtles, how comes it to paſs we have no mention of it in all the New Teſtament? VVhat daies were to be Obſerved by the <hi>Jews,</hi> are made mention of, over and over in the old Teſtament; how comes it to paſs, if <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Day, or other Days be to be Obſerved by Chriſtians, we find no mention of them in any of the Books of the New Scripture, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the nature of the Books of the two Teſtaments, and the Reaſon is Manifeſt For if you conſider the Old Teſtament, you will find not only Hiſtorical Books, ſuch are the books of <hi>Judges,</hi> the <hi>Kings &amp;c.</hi> and moral Books which treat of good Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch are the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, Eccleſiaſtes</hi> &amp; others: But beſides theſe, there are Ritual Books, which by the very ſubject of them every one ſees, their Deſign was to deſcribe the external Moſaical VVorſhip, as to Obſervation of Daies, Prieſtly Garments, Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such are the Books of <hi>Exodus, Leviticus,</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> And therefore no wonder if you find exactly ſet down, what Daies that people was to keep Holy, How their Prieſts were to be Conſecrated, and how Veſted in time of Divine Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But now caſt your Eye upon all the Books of the New-Teſtament, and you'l not find one that you can reaſonably preſume, the Author of it had a Deſign in it, to Deſcribe the External VVorſhip of the Goſpel: VVhat daies for Example, we Chriſtians are to obſerve in memory of Chriſtian Mercies and Miſters, what Garments our Prieſts are to uſe in Divine Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet the Light of God within us tells us, ſuch Inſtitutions are very uſeful to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Piety, when Religiouſly Obſerved: and all Hiſtory tells us, that immemorially in all Nations, there have been certain external Chriſtian Rites, not mentioned in the Holy Scriptures, ever ſince the firſt planting of Chriſtianity amongſt them. The four Goſpels are a Hiſtory of our Bleſſed Saviours Life and Death, who lived as to the external Rites of Religion according to the Jewiſh Law, and ſo we cannot reaſonably in any of them expect, what Days we Chriſtians are to obſerve in the time of the Goſpel. Indeed had the Acts of the Apoſtles been intended as an exact Narration, how the Apoſtles lived as to the whole courſe of their Life, what Days they kept Holy, and what Days they Faſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> VVe might reaſonably have expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome mention there of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day and <hi>Lent:</hi> But that Holy Book making mention only, of ſome few particular paſſages, of two or three of the Apoſtles Lives; the Apoſtles might well keep <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Day and <hi>Lent</hi> too, and teach them alſo to their firſt Converts, and yet there be a profound ſilence of ſuch Obſervations in the Book of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44969:6"/>their Acts. As for St. <hi>Johns</hi> Prophetical Book, it were no ways pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in it, to treat either of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day or <hi>Lent.</hi> Though <hi>I</hi> muſt tell you, for ought you or <hi>I</hi> know, when St. <hi>John</hi> ſays he was in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on the Lords Day, he may mean the Day of our Lords Birth, or the yearly <hi>Eaſter</hi> Day of his Reſurrection, as well as our VVeekly Sunday. The reſt of the New Teſtament are certain Epiſtles or Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſpiritual Counſels written by St. <hi>Paul</hi> or ſome other Apoſtle, to particular Perſons or whole Cities, already inſtructed in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an way of VVorſhip: But why they ſhould needs make mention therein of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Day, <hi>I</hi> underſtand not, unleſs perchance the Perſons they wrote unto, had been deficient in keeping it Holy.</p>
            <p>But, does not St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly deery the keeping of <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi>-Day, in one of his Epiſtles, and tells the Chriſtians he wrote to, he was afraid he had laboured in vain amongſt them, by reaſon of their Superſtitious Obſervation of Dayes. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>How are ye Converted again to weak and beggarly Elements, which you will Serve again? Ye obſerve Dayes, and Months, and Times and Years. I am afraid of you, leſt I ſhould have laboured amongſt you in Vain.</hi> Was then the Holy Apoſtle afraid, leſt the <hi>Galations</hi> ſhould leave Chriſtianity, and return to Judaiſm or Paganiſm, becauſe of their Obſerving <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi>-Day, in Memory of our Bleſſed Saviour's Birth, or Lent, in Memory of his Faſting forty Dayes, or <hi>Eaſter</hi> in Memory of his Reſurrection? Is this a likely Story? Or is it not evident from the Context, <hi>Of their returning again to weak and poor Elements,</hi> that becauſe of their returning to the Obſervation of <hi>Jewiſh-Dayes,</hi> Commanded by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi> Dayes, in honour of <hi>Jupiter, Mars,</hi> or <hi>Saturn,</hi> he was afraid they would Relinquiſh the Goſpel, by them Received, and become <hi>Jews</hi> again or <hi>Pagans.</hi> But, ſtill me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, I am afraid of Superſtition, and Will-Worſhip, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Day, which, I fear, God has never Commanded me. But you have more reaſon to be afraid of Prophaners, in neglecting a Day which you have all reaſon to think God has Commanded you to keep Holy, if you Reflect well upon what I have ſaid, above. Seeing you are Commanded to keep Holy <hi>Chriſtmaſs-Day,</hi> by doing only ſuch Actions, as you acknowledge to be Chriſtianly and Good, What danger can there be of Superſtition? Eſpecially, when you are not Taught neither, that ſuch Actions are then more acceptable to God Almighty, than at another times. Only, you are Commanded at that Set-Time to do them, leſt, otherwiſe, you ſhould wholly omit Them. My deereſt Relations (whom I pity with my Soul) take heed whilſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44969:6"/>under pretence of Oppoſing <hi>Anti-Chriſt,</hi> you be not one day found Abettors of <hi>Anti-Chriſt.</hi> Conſider, <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> is to Deny and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and then think, Who are more like <hi>Anti-Chriſt,</hi> thoſe who piouſly obſerve certain Dayes, in Memory of the Birth, Death, and Reſurrection of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or thoſe who prophane and decry all ſuch Dayes as Superſtitious? Who are moſt likely to promote <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi>'s Deſign, that is, to Abolliſh and Root all Memory of <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of the World, the Devout Obſervers, or Irreligious Prophaners of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Solemnities?</p>
            <p>But were it not better, to remember and ponder the Myſtery of our Lord's Nativity, with it's circumſtances every day? No, He that would graſp many things together, holds faſt few, or perhaps none. The capacity of our Souls is ſo limited, that if we would have the Thoughts of our Lord's humble Nativity ſink deep into us, and efficaciouſly work the ſpiritual Fruit they are apt to work in us, we muſt entertain them, and no other but them for a good ſeaſon together, and repeat them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over. He that will pretend to have all ſorts of ſpiritual Thoughts every day, will I fear, upon no day, have any to any Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual purpoſe. Let us not pretend to be wiſer than God Almighty. He ordered the <hi>Jews,</hi> and he has ordered us Chriſtians alſo, a grateful Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spiritual Seaſons. Let it therefore be concluded againſt the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> (the All-Merciful Jeſus open their Eyes) that a Religious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> has nothing of Superſtition, but a great deal of Chriſtian Piety in it.</p>
            <p>And now, we are reſolved <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> ought to be kept, but how muſt we keep it? If any Man keep a day, let him keep it to the Lord: So as his keeping of it may not Contriſtate, but Recreate, and Rejoyce his Dear and Greateſt Lord: So, as his keeping of it, may make him all the Year after, more ſtrong and ready, to imitate and tread in the Steps (as neer as Humane-Frailty will permit,) of his ſame Lord Let now this Holy time be ſpent, as to the far greateſt part of it, in devout Prayers, frequent Meditations upon the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Solemnity, Reading Spiritual Books, Hearing Sermons ſuited to the occaſion; Giving large Alms to God Almighty in his poor and needy, in gratitude to him, who at this time gave as no leſs than his only Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the truth is, that which makes many well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and tenderly Conſcientious Chriſtians, to make no diſtinction of this Sacred Time, from another, was the intolerable abuſe of it, by its pretended Religious Obſervers. Time would fail me, if I ſhould go about to enumerate the Debaucherys, with which this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44969:7"/>Time has been prophaned. May they never be Remembred, unleſs it be to VVeep for them, and to excite our ſelves to make amends for them, by a double diligence in all Holy and Chriſtian Exerciſes, theſe Daies of Chriſt. Had this holy Time been ever ſpent, according to its Primitive Inſtitution in more abundant VVorks of Piety and Charity: And when our Spirits had been wearied out with Spiritual exerciſes; had we refreſhed Nature by a Feſtival Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, or ſome harmleſs Diſport; but ſtill with a vigilant Watch in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Sacred Seaſon, ſo to play, as our Paſtime might not make our Great little Jeſus VVeep: Had, <hi>I</hi> ſay, this Holy Time been ever thus holily Obſerved, the Devil himſelf could not have had the Impudence, to have declared againſt it, as Antichriſtian. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as it has been of late Obſerved, or rather Prophaned, we may without a ſlander, ſay, it was become a truly Antichriſtian Time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>But what Remedy then? Abandon the new prophane Abuſe, and tetrive the firſt pious Uſe. But what Fruit may we expect from a Religious Obſervation of this Holy Time? Obſerve it, as was ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and you'l be better able to tell me afterwards at <hi>Twelf-tide,</hi> then I can tell you before, on <hi>Chriſtmaſs-Eve.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Gloria in Excelſis Deo.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44969:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
